<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"[
<!ENTITY imgroot "images/tools/ruta/language/" >
<!ENTITY % uimaents SYSTEM "../../target/docbook-shared/entities.ent" >  
%uimaents;
]>
<!-- Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more contributor 
  license agreements. See the NOTICE file distributed with this work for additional 
  information regarding copyright ownership. The ASF licenses this file to 
  you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may not use 
  this file except in compliance with the License. You may obtain a copy of 
  the License at http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0 Unless required 
  by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software distributed under the 
  License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS 
  OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See the License for the specific 
  language governing permissions and limitations under the License. -->

<section id="ugr.tools.ruta.language.anchoring">
  <title>Matching order</title>
  <para>
    If not specified otherwise, then the UIMA Ruta rules normally start the matching 
    process with their first rule element. The first rule element searches for possible positions for its matching
    condition and then will advise the next rule element to continue the matching process.
    For that reason, writing rules that contain a first rule element with an optional quantifier is discouraged 
    and will result in ignoring the optional attribute of the quantifier.
  </para>
  <para>
    The starting rule element can also be manually specified by adding <quote>@</quote> directly in front of the matching condition.
    In the following example, the rule first searches for capitalized words (CW) and then checks whether 
    there is a period in front of the matched word.
    <programlisting><![CDATA[PERIOD @CW;]]></programlisting>
    This functionality can also be used for rules that start with an optional rule element by manually specifying a later
    rule element to start the matching process.
  </para>
  <para>
    The choice of the starting rule element can greatly influence the performance speed of the rule execution. 
    This circumstance is illustrated with the following example that contains two rules, whereas already an annotation 
    of the type <quote>LastToken</quote> was added to the last token of the document:
    <programlisting><![CDATA[ANY LastToken;
ANY @LastToken;]]></programlisting>
    The first rule matches on each token of the document and checks whether the next annotation is the last token of the document.
    This will result in many index operations because all tokens of the document are considered. 
    The second rule, however, matches on the last token and then checks if there is any token in front of it. This
    rule, therefore, considers only one token. 
  </para>
  <para>
    The UIMA Ruta language provides also a concept for automatically selecting the starting rule element called dynamic anchoring.
    Here, a simple heuristic concerning the position of the rule element and the involved types is applied in order to identify
    the favorable rule element. This functionality can be activated in the <link linkend="ugr.tools.ruta.ae.basic.parameter">configuration parameters</link> of the analysis engine or 
    directly in the script file with the <link linkend="ugr.tools.ruta.language.actions.dynamicanchoring">DYNAMICANCHORING</link> action. 
  </para>
</section>